<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proceedings concerning the improvement of all manner of land, and also for all sorts of leather VVith many addresses unto Parliaments, and other supreme authorities formerly in power. As also petitional motions unto the supreme authority of this nation, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the dominions and territories thereunto belonging, that they would be pleased to make use of the proposer, in entertaining his abilities with acts of Parliament, according to the lawes of this and all civil nations; that then thereby he may be impowred lawfully and honourable to put in exercise his undertakings: the profitable effects and conveniences of them being hereafter sufficiently proved and cleared. All which designes are undertaken to be performed by new wayes and means, more speedy, cheap and easie than hath hitherto been discovered, and are acquired by the industry and diligent search into the mysteries of nature, of Thomas Ducket, Esq; very well deserving the perusal of persons of all degrees ... prosperity of the Commonwealth.</title>
            <author>Duckett, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2430C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897641</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2513:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proceedings concerning the improvement of all manner of land, and also for all sorts of leather VVith many addresses unto Parliaments, and other supreme authorities formerly in power. As also petitional motions unto the supreme authority of this nation, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the dominions and territories thereunto belonging, that they would be pleased to make use of the proposer, in entertaining his abilities with acts of Parliament, according to the lawes of this and all civil nations; that then thereby he may be impowred lawfully and honourable to put in exercise his undertakings: the profitable effects and conveniences of them being hereafter sufficiently proved and cleared. All which designes are undertaken to be performed by new wayes and means, more speedy, cheap and easie than hath hitherto been discovered, and are acquired by the industry and diligent search into the mysteries of nature, of Thomas Ducket, Esq; very well deserving the perusal of persons of all degrees ... prosperity of the Commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>Duckett, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Leach,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>May the last, 1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>DFo copy, reel 2513, is trimmed at head and foot affecting paging and signatures.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Duckett, Thomas --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inventions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>CEEDINGS</hi> Concerning the Improvement of all manner of LAND, And alſo for all ſorts of LEATHER.</p>
            <p>VVith many Addreſſes unto Parliaments, and other Supreme Authorities formerly in Power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AS ALSO</hi> Petitional Motions unto the ſupreme Authority of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging, that they would be pleaſed to make uſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer, in entertaining his abilities with Acts of Parliament, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lawes of this and all Civil Nations; that then there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may be impowred lawfully and honourably to put in exerciſe his undertakings: The profitable Effects and Conveniences of them being hereafter ſufficiently proved and cleared.</p>
            <p>All which Deſignes are undertaken to be performed by new wayes and means, more ſpeedy, cheap and eaſie than hath hitherto been diſcovered, and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the Induſtry and diligent ſearch into the Myſteries of Nature,</p>
            <p>Of <hi>THOMAS DUCKET,</hi> Eſq</p>
            <p>Very well deſerving the peruſal of perſons of all degrees, that love ingenuity, and the more flouriſhing proſperity of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Leach, May</hi> the laſt, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Honours,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe alterations in State affairs, and other occurrences, being ſo many as are hereafter publiſhed, do therefore require this Preface or Introduction, whereby to give ſatisfaction unto your Honours and all good people that have ſo long expected the fruition of what is here tendred.</p>
            <p>The Contents of all after repetitions giving ſufficient proof and reaſon to convince all Objections and croſſe Arguments; As alſo a Breviate of his Bills as they were prepared by Councel Learned in the Law, and afterwards approved of by Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of a former Parliament, deputed for that purpoſe, who made their report of the ſaid Bills, as alſo of the Propoſers ability to perform the Contents therein conteined, when they ſhould be paſſed into Acts of Parliament. And although the intent of all that is hereafter declared may ſeem tedious in the peruſal, yet queſtionleſſe your Honours and all worthy Peruſers will think the time well ſpent, for that many Ages never had the like Tender, nor have delayed ſuch hopefull Succeſſes; and therefore might have required a larger Scope to demonſtrate the great benefits this Nation might long before this time have received, if that ſuch cauſes as are after recited, had not obſtructed the Settlement.</p>
            <p>And that your Honours may receive an Account from the Propoſer why he doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate, and drive ſo cloſe and home againſt perſons that he doth conceive to have been, and likely to be, Antagoniſts to ſuch rich and tranſcendent hopes; although no ſuch perſon hath as yet publiſhed himſelf in print to be an Enemy to theſe new princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſo held forth; for anſwer thereto I am to let your Honours underſtand.</p>
            <p>Firſt, albeit none but of unreaſonable impudence, and depraved nature, dare let the world judge of their Folly, by ſubſcribing their Names to ſuch a dangerous diſcompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a national benefit, notwithſtanding their high pitch in Envy; yet they dare vent their ſpightfull invectives againſt the Propoſer in malicious and contemptible frothy diſcourſes behind his back; ſo that ſince his firſt Addreſſes, which were many years agoe, the Propoſer hath been ſubject to the preſſure of Multiplicity of provocations in ſeveral companies by ſpightfull and perverſe Detractors, in headleſſe and abſurd Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, eſpecially by thoſe who have thought themſelves pregnant and Powerfull; and there can hardly be a greater plague upon Earth, than to be liable to Evill Tongues, and Cenſures, as the Propoſer hath alwayes been, which cannot be redreſſed, for that the Company of thoſe ſelf-conceited Criticks, who will rail againſt any mans principles but their own, are numerous, and it is better to have one, two, or three, of ſuch Malevolent ſpirits to anſwer unto, if they durſt publiſh their Malignancy in writing, than a thouſand others, whom reaſon will not ſatisfie, but will at all times, and in all companies, belch forth their ſpight and Envy againſt any thing which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds their common capacities; but this many times turns to their own diſgrace and ſhame, when the Propoſer diſcerneth juſt cauſe to joyn in contest with them, ſome part of their preſumption ariſing from the Propoſers long delay in gaining an authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:133314:2"/> to put in Execution what he hath ſo long held forth, and divers other uncought Arguments, as barren of reaſon as that aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>But the Propoſers cauſe be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng juſt, doth give him the advantage to maſter them by Reaſon, and confute them by Arguments, ſo much as is ſufficient to daſh out of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance any unbelieving Criticks, Buſie-bodies, Quibling Sophiſters, Pickthanks, trifling Ieerers, Buffoons, or froward Humoriſts, compoſed of indigeſted Ignorance; and the virtue of thoſe Truths, which the Propoſer holds forth, doth ſo much out bear their brain-ſick Arguments, that it doth increaſe the Malevolency of their Spleens, to malign all his proceedings with Gall and bitterneſſe, which is the cauſe this relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo fully proved, to give ſuch Evidence, as may convince them in behalf of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is high time for the Propoſer to apply himſelf to your Honours for a ſpeedy Settlement of the Premiſſes, to the end that he may perform ſuch ſervice to the Nation, as may quite extinguiſh all contradiction by cavelling Detractors, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe who are impudently reſolved neither to ſee or hear, although their own Conſcience convince them, and bring them to the unwor hy Odium in the old Proverb, being there is none ſo blind, as thoſe that will not ſee, and none ſo deaf, as thoſe that will not hear.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe, by way of Addreſſe, the Propoſer could preſent no leſſe than what doth hereafter follow: for of neceſſity there muſt be the full ſubſtance and property of his deſigns, with their proofs of performance, and anſwers unto all ſelf-ended Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and cavelling Expreſſions, touching the commodity or diſcommodities of Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, together with the Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſers juſtification of his perſon and reputation, and proofs and atteſtations of his knowledge and abilities, as alſo of the high Degree and Magnitude of what he hath attained unto in Natures Storehouſe, with many liberal applauſes of the virtue of his new Enterpriſes, and with more reiterations, than is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual in repugning, and publikely defying perſons that formerly have, and ſtill may, breath noiſome Air againſt laudable Actions, that are above their Meridian, and are thereby prodigious to their own good, and the Nations pleaſure and plenty.</p>
            <p>And alſo treating of the glory that your Honours may attain unto, by entertaining theſe Tenders, which conduce to a national Improvement, and therefore with good cauſe, humbly craving your Honours ſerious vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w and rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew of the Propoſers real integrity in theſe works tendred, wherein your Honours will diſcern juſt cauſe for all theſe enſuing expreſſions, and will thereby the better be induced to hold excuſed, all the reherſals and recitals in this dictate, that could not be explained without reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and repetition, to introduce ſome addition of new matter, fit for obſervation, though much of affinity with what hath been aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And although the full obſervation of the contents, and the many large promiſes there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n conteined, may unto the vulgar capacities ſeem oſtentatious; Yet your Honours prudence will on the contrary weigh them as they are, touching an vniverſal benefit, and that theſe new diſcoveries may be a preferment to the Nation in general, or to Nations generally, and your Honours will perceive juſt cauſe to confeſſe, that the Theori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Methoditical, and Practical proceedings in renowned enterprizes, ought to be ſupported with a more Magiſterial fullneſſe in words, than can belong to the hope of gaining ſome ſmall profit, of little value, and ſhort continuance: And therefore by your Honours cannot be eſteemed vain boaſting: But if there ſhould eſcape my pen ſome faulty branches, yet I hope it may in wiſdome by your Honours receive a pardon, according to the Proverb, of giving a loſer leave to speak, that hath spent and diſburſed the beſt of his years and the beſt of his eſtate in this faithful ſervice, and hath had no encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement,
<pb facs="tcp:133314:3"/> or returns ſuitable to his merits, the which would nettle the pen of any b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Naturalliſts, who do ſtudy &amp; obſerve the conditions f men, with as much circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spection as they do the natures of Creatures, Minerals, and Vegetatives, by which inspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, they have acquired ſo much diſcretion as to ſleight and invalue thoſe conſtitutions, whoſe natures want true ſeaſon, or ſome degrees of concoction, to operate in fullneſſe of vertue and knowledge, the which the Propoſer doth repreſent to your Honours, as a juſt reaſon of the great pains and much patience the Propoſer is driven unto, in ſeeking meanes by all lenity to convince erronious opinions, by offering all manner of curteſie and civil argument, to their curſt contradictions, thereby to calm them with Reaſons, and ſatisfactory Arguments: for the Propoſer hath no other way to qualify their Malice, unleſſe it were in giving ſome of the chiefeſt in pride and preſumption, ſome ſpecial ſhare and partnerſhip, in the honour and profit which ought to accrue unto the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and his poſterity, by virtue of thoſe Trophees, that Nature and Induſtry hath indowed him withall.</p>
            <p>And therefore for quietneſſe ſake, and a more eaſie proceeding, that the way may be cleared of all ſuch interruptions to a national good, The Propoſer could have willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereunto condeſcended, but that the Heraulds at Arms, and other honorable Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaries, would have thereby juſt cauſe to take Recognizance of the Propoſers Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, as to the diſgrace of his Name, Deſcent, and Pedigree, whereof he is ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and tender, that whenſoever he doth make room for ſuch a blot againſt his Friends, and falſity againſt himſelf, then let thoſe Officers aforeſaid, joyn in defacing his anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Coat of Arms, by creating the Embleme of ſome corrupt vermine or beaſt of prey, to be placed upon the Authors antient Coat of Arms,<note place="margin">The Creſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Arms of <hi>Ducket,</hi> is an Oſtrige feather gules invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned in a Crownet of Gold.</note> inſtead of the preſent Creſt, as an alluſion that he ſo unworthily ſubmitted to pragmattick greedy perſons fraighted with Avarice, but empty of Goodneſſe, and that Falſehood had overcome Truth, contrary to the known Maxim.</p>
            <p>And thus the Propoſer in his faithfull indulgence to your Honours, and the weal pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, could not poſſibly ſay any thing leſſe, than what is herein, and in the enſuing Relation to be expreſſed, the length and prolixity whereof, he hopes will be the rather diſpenced withall, becauſe that things of ſo large and general a concernment, could not without prejudice and Injury to the matter be wound up and concluded in ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a brevity as proceedings of ſmall conſequence; yet all the contents require not above the twelfth part of a Natural day to be peruſed, ſcanned, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of; But becauſe many perſons cannot admit of ſo much time to peruſe the whole, the Propoſer thought it neceſſary to give ſome good part of ſatisfaction in every page, or leaf; the contents whereof, with all humble ſubmiſſion, the Propoſer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs to your Honours great wiſdomes, as alſo what may ſeem improper or imperfect in this dictate, or the Printers miſtakes, the Propoſer doth likewiſe ſubmit, having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy too much intrenched upon your Honours patience, who are further to be uſed in the premiſſes and; therefore, what ever elſe ought to have been ſaid, yet in good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and order, there muſt no more bee ſaid, but only that the Propoſer in all conſtant faithfullneſſe is reſolved to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours in all devout and devoted Obedience,</hi> Thomas Ducket:</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:3"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the Proceedings of <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> Eſq <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking.</note> by his great charge and ſtudy in Natures operation, hath (by Gods aſſiſtance) diſcovered ſeveral rich, and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Secrets, Arts and Myſteries, for the Improvement of all ſorts of Land, by deſtroying of all ſorts of Weeds, Traſh, Shrubs, and other Incumbrances, Raiſing of Waters, Creating of a new ſoil or manure; To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with more expeditions cheap and eaſie actions, and motions to perform the ſame; And likewiſe for the improvement of Leather of all ſorts, in excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and perfection of Strength, Grain, and Colour, being deſigns of great honour and plenty for <hi>Engliſh</hi> People.</p>
            <p>The Real performance of which Inventions, firſt as to Land,<note place="margin">The reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his inventions for land atteſted by many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and quality.</note> was teſtified by Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates under the hands of many perſons of Honour and qualitie of ſeveral Counties unto you the Right Honourable Members of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, not long before your Honours were diſturbed, being in <hi>April</hi> the 23. 1653. for before thoſe accidents, and alterations in State, your Petitioner did daily ſolicit the worthy and moſt renowned members of this Parliament then ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that they would be pleas'd to peruſe and take into conſideration in the Houſe, the Bill he had prepared by Council learned in the Law, to be paſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Act for improvement of Land. But multiplicity of State-affairs (as it ſeem'd) or elſe new inventions in theſe <hi>Septe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trional</hi> Countries ſeeming ſtrange,<note place="margin">New in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions being a wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r to the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath been a chief <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora.</hi>
               </note> or elſe National Malediction did retard the ſettlement of ſuch good fortune, notwithſtanding the exact and clear deſcriptions of the particulars, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of many honourable and worthy perſons as aforeſaid, who atteſted, and largely ſatisfied your Honours of the Propoſer's ability to perform his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings: yet nevertheleſſe your Honours not putting a diſpatch to ſo great a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional advantage, occaſioned a doubtfulneſſe in the Propoſer, leſt his publick ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, amongſt the generality of people, might be reflected on him as nothing but pretences; and that he were not able to ſet forth any additional thing that were rich, and good for improvement of Land, more than what former ages, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time had, or have produced. And there upon the Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſer, minding the good of his Native Country, and the honour of his own reputation, to avoid all jealouſies, miſtakes, and controverſies of any doubtful, captious perſons, who through their own imbecillity might conceit that what he had ſo held forth were but a ſuperficial ſhew, without any reality at all; or if he were a maſter of ſuch skill,<note place="margin">No cauſe of neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo good a tender, for three reaſons.</note> that then it was bottomed beyond the reach of ordinary underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſo deep, that it did require long conſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ration, and State policie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the depth, ſcope and centre thereof; although the caſe is evident, clear, and void of all ſuſpition and controverſie, and would be ſpeedily embraced in any Southern Nation, for theſe three reaſons, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for that it cannot chooſe but be a univerſal benefit to any Nation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe no Stateſman, nor any belonging to them, or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:133314:4"/> ſhall be charged with any coſt, trouble, or damage, until he have a full knowledge, and poſſeſſion of the skill.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, no perſon is, nor ſhall be compelled, without his eſpecial deſire and conſent, to make uſe of any of the ſaid Inventions, or to take a licenſe for that purpoſe, neither is any man to be reſtrained by vertue of ſuch an act, from making uſe of all, &amp; all manner of courſes in husbandry, Arts and Myſteries, that have ever formerly been uſed, or are at this preſent in common uſe and practice, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred of any of their accuſtomed exerciſes, but only of thoſe new diſcoveries, and additions to former practices, which are and ſhall be publiſhed and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted.</p>
            <p>Therefore to prevent theſe and ſuch doubts, ſuppoſitions, and other obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Propoſer having long ſince by his ſtudies in the myſteries of Nature, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a moſt ſtrange, and unheard of ſecret, never before diſcovered, in this or former ages, which is of ſo high a degree of Conſequence, in richneſſe, and rarity of art,<note place="margin">The Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all dubious minds, and to make known his ability in Land, did demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate his skill in the myſtery of Leather.</note> that for the convincing of all erroneous minds, thoughts and words, as to his ability in knowledge, He did by his new inventions, convert many ſcore of raw hides, and skins into leather, without Bark of Oaks, Aſh, or any other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed ingredients; as alſo did make leather of a more rich and profitable condition, than ever yet was known, by aſſiſting, and bettering of all former known practices, with new means, and additional ingredients, and liquors to be mixed and compounded with bark of Oaks, and all others formerly uſed, which is, and may be performed eaſier, ſpeedier, and with leſſe charge than formerly: which did, doth, and may demonſtrate his knowledge to be far more profound, and beyond the reach of all ſorts of Artificers, although they have been Maſters of ſuch practice as hath ever been by tradition uſed <hi>ſince this part of the world was civil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which the Propoſer hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in the ſaid art and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers skill and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>Yet notwithſtanding the higheſt degree of perfection that they have attain'd unto by their long practice, by way of embleme and pattern, to make an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictable certainty in the judgement of all wiſe and judicious perſons, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer having atchieved the knowledge, did produce that moſt admirable Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece for all that are concerned in Leather, that thereby your Honours, and the world may know, that his reach and underſtanding in improvement of the ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of all ſorts of lands, doth, and may in all likelyhood in the particulars of his intended diſcoveries, as much ſurmount the practice of any Actors, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors in Husbandry.</p>
            <p>And upon theſe grounds the Propoſer took the pains to demonſtrate the great Myſtery for Leather, before he had any Act for the improvement of land: but if an Act for improvement of land had been granted, his actions had been ſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant to the purpoſe, beyond what is practiſed by others, as would have induced ſuch a full belief with your Honours, or any other ſupreme perſons authorized, that his own promiſe and aſſertion, would have ſupported his undertakings as to Leather, to be of ſuch current truth, that his pains in ſetting forth a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of tanning of Leather according to the new myſtery, might have been ſpared as a needleſſe impertinency.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers good will to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit his native Country, did cauſe him to neglect no opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to get a ſettlement of his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>But the Propoſer obſerving the variety of minds, and tempers of people, and changes of government, with the like, did hold it neceſſary to make the world ſenſible of his abilities by thoſe actions, as aforeſaid, and then when he had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo good a belief, it had been a great want of prudence and good mind in the Propoſer, if he ſhould have neglected his addreſſes to any ſupreme Authority
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133314:4"/> that next enſued your Honours. Firſt, in regard that he was ſtricken in yeares: Next, becauſe he had a great zeal to lend his aſſiſtance to help his own Native Countrey, before any forein Nation, and ſome other cauſes ſupported by the rule of diſcretion, occaſioned him in an elaborate way to make his addreſſes unto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſort of ſupreme Authority, from the diſſolution of your Honours as aforeſaid until this preſent time; and that he might be more certain of gaining an authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the exerciſing of what he ſo held forth, he firſt cleared all doubts and queries by ſignificant demonſtration of ſeveral parcels of Leather ſo tanned and tawed; and likewiſe by certificates thereupon from moſt of the chief Tanners, and other tradeſmen as to Leather, of ſeveral Counties in and about <hi>London,</hi> to his late Highneſſe <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector, and his Council, and likewiſe to the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee for trade, then in power, the which Committee by order ſummoned a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous company of Tanners, and other tradeſmen as to Leather, to give their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and teſtimony of the ſaid Leather, the which perſons ſo ſummoned, did not only under their hands, but likewiſe themſelves in perſon, affirm and teſtifie of the goodneſſe of the ſaid Leather, and of the ability of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> to perform his undertakings, and of the great benefit that would ariſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to the three Nations, and earneſtly requeſted a ſpeedy ſettlement of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes.</p>
            <p>By the means of which proceedings,<note place="margin">His late Highneſſe <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector's grant of Patents.</note> his late Highneſſe <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector with his Council were ſo fully ſatisfied herein, that his Highneſſe forthwith granted the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> two ſeveral Patents for the ſole exerciſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his ſaid inventions for improvement of Land and Leather for fourteen years; which upon conſideration, and peruſal by the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi>'s Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in the Law, they were found not to be of ſufficient power and validitie to make him a ſecure title, by reaſon of the multitude of the people he was to deal with, as to land, and certain Statutes, and eſpecially ſome Statutes as to Leather, prohibiting the uſe of any other liquors or ingredients, but Bark of Oaks, and other ingredients then in uſe, and limiting ſet times in Tannage; the maker of ſuch Statutes (by all likelihood) not imagining that any better way or inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could be found out, by the means whereof it proved this nations unhappineſs,<note place="margin">Reaſons why the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents were of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity.</note> to be ſuppreſſed, delayed, &amp; hazarded in the hope of the accommodation of thoſe rich &amp; precious benefits that might then ſpeedily have enſued by power of Broad-Seal Patents, if thoſe foreſaid old acts had not fruſtrated the progreſſe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the premiſes.</p>
            <p>For although it fell out, that thoſe old barres in Law proved to be againſt the law of right and reaſon, yet nevertheleſſe there was no remedy to avoid the ſame, although it were to the daily loſſe and prejudice of the people, and muſt have ſo continued, until the errors of thoſe former Parliament lawes were through the prudence of ſome new Parliament-Magiſtrates, diſcerned, deſerted, and repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to make way for better opportunities, and then the Propoſer by a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary act impowred.</p>
            <p>And upon theſe, and ſome other accounts and procraſtinations, the ſaid <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Ducket</hi> was in reaſon neceſſitated to forbear the diſcovery of his deſigned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and ſo did untill there was a Parliament aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in <hi>September</hi> 1656. where then the Propoſer after addreſſing himſelf and his cauſe unto them, then after ſufficient debate, and through the virtue of ſeveral Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates from many worthy Patriots conducing to land, as alſo the new teſtimony of his late Highneſſe <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector and his Council, as to Land and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133314:5"/> as alſo the Certificate of the chiefeſt Tanners,<note place="margin">The Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe and certificates to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees for Trade, of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers ability</note> and other tradeſmen as to Leather, recommended unto the ſaid Parliament, together wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the appearance of numerous companies of Tanners, and other dealers in Leather, at ſeveral times, did make their perſonal addreſſe unto the whole body of the houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that behalf, and alſo when occaſion required did preſent themſelves at other times, unto ſeveral Committees of Parliament, and at laſt through very much inveterate trouble, perplexity, tediouſneſſe incident to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proceedings; afterwards this enſuing report was made in anſwer to a grand Committee of that Parliament, by power of an Order granted by them unto a Sub-Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, the words being thus returned, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="report">
               <body>
                  <head>The Report.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a Committee of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>IN obſervance of an Order of this Committee, bearing date the 23. day of <hi>December</hi> laſt, we have examined, and conſidered of the propoſals and new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> Eſq for the improvement of all ſorts of lands, and alſo for the converting all ſorts of raw hides, and skins into leather, without Bark of Oaks, or other uſual ingredients; &amp; upon conference with him, his reaſons and demonſtrations hath given us good ſatisfaction, as well of his abilities, as of the benefit that may come to this Commonwealth thereby, and we are the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to believe the ſame, for that his Highneſſe and Council have certified on his behalf, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kewiſe many other perſons of worth and quality in ſeveral Counties to the ſame effect.</p>
                  <p>And we do farther report, that we have ſuperviſed his bills for improvement of Lands and Leather, and have made many alterations and reſtrictions therein, and do humbly conceive that the ſaid <hi>Thomas Duckets</hi> undertakings deſerve all due incouragement, that this Commonwealth may enjoy the benefit thereof.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated <date>the 1. of <hi>May.</hi> 1657</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>The Committee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of 5 or 6 but any three of two were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred to report.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Henry Pickering.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Timbs.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Robert Weſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The bills likewiſe prepared by the ſaid Commi tee. Sir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Picke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to move it in the houſe.</note>After the return of this report from the Sub-Committee unto the Grand Committee, together with the two bills for Land and Leather, as they were prepared and made fit to be enacted, it was then reſolved, and ſo ordered by that Grand Committee, that the then <hi>Henry Pickering</hi> Eſq now <hi>Henry Pickering</hi> Knight, one of the Sub-Committees (whoſe name is unto the ſaid report) ſhould with all convenient ſpeed, wait the Houſe daily for an opportunity, and there to move the Right Honourable Speaker Sir <hi>Thomas Widdringto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to give way for the publication of thoſe bills ſo prepared; and the ſaid Honourable Speaker was made acquainted therewith, who was very writing to give way to the ſaid Sir <hi>Henry Pickerings</hi> motion, in cauſing the bills to be read, and he in his loyalty and goodneſs to the Wealpublick (being well ſatisfied of the propoſers ability, and the great advantage that hereby might ariſe to the Nation) was contented to aſſiſt thoſe proceedings; and rather then the buſineſs ſhould receive any delay by the motion of Sir <hi>Henry Pickering,</hi> he was honourably pleaſed that thoſe bills ſhould be moved as private bills by himſelf;<note place="margin">Cauſe why the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was not ſetled.</note> but juſt at the time when moſt of the Members were acquainted with theſe Proceedings, and were in a readineſs to give audience as to a ſettlement, then it ſo pleaſed God that the ſaid <hi>Thomas
<pb facs="tcp:133314:5"/> Ducket</hi> was viſited with ſickneſſe, ſo that he could not attend the Houſe, but was forced to let his buſineſs lye dormant and proceed no farther; in which time of his ſickneſſe, the Parliament was firſt adjourned, and after their next ſitting ſuddainly diſſolved; And now through providence your Honours (with whom were my firſt proceedings and addre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es) being reinveſted with the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority, from whence this Nation may receive thoſe fortunate ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which are to be preſented by the Propoſer, who hath the good fate once more to make his Addreſſes to your Honours, although at preſent your Honours are full of publick employment,<note place="margin">The deſigns are of ſo great worth that they merit the reſult of the Parliament, more than any other buſineſſe except the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Nation.</note> yet the Propoſer well knowing (that ſetting aſide the ſecurity of the Nation) there is not any thing in the Houſe in agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that may better advance a flouriſhing plentie to your Honours and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, than the entertainment of the premiſſes, which in the peircing eye of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is a moſt notable, pretious, publick buſineſs, and cannot be denied in the Reaſon, Judgement, and Wiſdom of your Honours, although this Nation is haunted with ſome injurious ignorant perſons, that will not ſtick to affirm it to be but a private buſineſs, in regard that the Owner, Founder, and Meſſenger of this myſtery, lays claim (according to the Law of Nations) to be gratified for fourteen years with ſome ſmall diminutive reward; whoſe penurious unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy condition'd language,<note place="margin">Sordid Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niations by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors.</note> or cuſtomary equivocation to quibble this Land out of a Succeſs and Character, muſt needs conſiſt of a peſtiferous male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to all ingenuity, inſomuch that they do endeavour to blaſt the glorious Law of National requital of laborious Maſters in profitable new diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, with the odium of Monopolies,<note place="margin">And other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villations.</note> unleſs that ſuch invertors of rich enterpriſes and high diſcoveries, do give the honour and profit thereof, unto the Members of State, and be content to ſtand unto their reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and queſtionleſs there are many, that will whiſper ſome great m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to that purpoſe, although thoſe ſo whiſpered cannot but diſcern, that they, with thoſe pickthank Flatteries, would fain allure Magiſtracy, into a Monopolizing thoſe atchievments which they never ſought nor ſweat for. And if your Honours do by Argument and Reaſon contradict thoſe Motioners, as to a courſe improper, yet they, or ſuch as they are, will ſtart ſome other quaery, ſaying, Why ſhould not the Inventor diſcloſe all his skill and manner of action, as well as demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration (unto ſome great Members of Parliament) in every particular,<note place="margin">Reaſons that the Propoſers undertakings are not to be diſcovered to any Members of Parliament, or others, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſettlement firſt granted.</note> before that he hath an Act paſſed? And that it were good policy in any Committee to urge and preſs the Propoſer home to that point. Now then, when any of your Honours do reply, (as queſtionleſs you may and will) That, if that the skill were made known to any Members of State, that then, they the ſaid Members are bound, by virtue of their truſt, to publiſh all politick profits to the Nation, without any impoſition of payment for any skill, that is before-hand made known, unto their repreſentative, who, by receiving ſuch intelligence from the Inventor, were thereby diſabled to make a Law to that effect: And that the Maſter of thoſe Myſteries may better diſpenſe with the breach of promiſe unto his particular;<note place="margin">☜</note> than the whole Nation with the truſt repoſed in any of its Members.<note place="margin">A diſcovery in reaſon not to be requested be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Again it may be anſwered (queſtionleſs) that the Propoſer will not yield unto any ſuch thing, in that the likelyhood of the profits of his diſcoveries, do farr ſurmount (as to the benefit of the Common-wealth) the valew of ten, twenty, or forty Gentlemens Eſtates, ſetting their places or power aſide: And again, that thoſe perſons that are ſtudious in any mental myſteries, and are of perfect knowledge therein, doubtleſs are ſo Judicious, that they will not deliver their principles
<pb facs="tcp:133314:6"/> to the poſſeſſion of others upon any ſuch uncertainties,<note place="margin">The inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience that may ariſe to the Propoſer and others by making a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery to any without an Act.</note> nor will they be guided in any unſtable courſe, for fear of loſing their benefits, and making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a ſimple Preſident to other Authors and Founders; neither will it become Members of State (in point of honour of the whole houſe) to motion any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign unto the Propoſer concerning his inventions, wherein there were any doubt of hazard; and for him the Propoſer, to ſubmit to ſuch adventures, is too much below the Honour of a perſon ſo endowed.</p>
            <p>And thus with trouble and woful experience, the Propoſer is able to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racterize the diſſerviceable part of thoſe puzzling Inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndiaries, that out of ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour will endeavour to foreſtall all good actions and intentions, whereby your Honours may eaſily diſcern, that their prating and practice hath a great affinity, with the skill and artifice of <hi>Achitophel;</hi> theſe their agitations plainly ſhewing, that ſuch perſons are none of thoſe godly wiſe men,<note place="margin">What kind of perſons Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors are, and from whence their natures are, and what is predominate over them, and what they are addicted to.</note> who, as the Scripture ſaith, doe command the ſtars; For certainly, theſe wretches, for want of Grace, do permit malevolent planets to predominate over them, even to the naturalizing of their minds, to the love of miſchief to others, and the impoveriſhing of all but themſelves, they being owners of ſome ſmall heap of droſſie ſubſtance, ſo much as doth advance and ſupport them ſo to overlook other mens matters as to breed diſturbances, controverſies, and cruelties, or elſe they would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and monopolize ſo many inſolencies, to divert the Settlement of Plentie.</p>
            <p>And certainly thoſe that have been adverſe to theſe proceedings are none of the wiſeſt, in ſeeking to hinder themſelves from the good ſucceſſe of profitable inventions atcheived by ingenuity; it may be they may be wittie, craftie, ſubtile, and inplacably politick, but yet want Judgement to diſcern, that there is no profit on the face of the earth, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his firſt entrance of ſettlement, with ſo little charge and pains as new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered myſteries; For in all ſea practices and proceedings, and all land affairs and actions, the events require charge, time, venture, loſſe and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,<note place="margin">No perſon at one penny charge in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very but the Propoſer. ☞</note> and many times ill ſucceſſe doth croſſe thoſe enterpriſes: But in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of theſe proceedings, to accommodate the Nation with knowledge, there is not one penny loſſe, not a ſheet of paper to any Clerk, nor fee to a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Officer, but what muſt and ſhall be ſatisfied by the Propoſer, after that your Honours have breathed out the concluding vote of an Act for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>It hath been reported, that <hi>Charls</hi> the fifth Emperour, and <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> called by his Subjects <hi>Philip</hi> the wiſe,<note place="margin">☞</note> and other Monarchs great in wiſdome and power, ſaid, it was very fitting that if it did ſo fall out that any perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to them, did pretend a new diſcovery of any new Art or Science, or profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Manufactory, if it were tendred without a charge, or coſt at firſt entrance and entertainment thereof, that all ſuch affairs ſhould be lovingly embraced by all men of reaſon, firſt for avoyding the diſcouragement of induſtry, Secondly, for that if any one rarity of new skill, or but any part of a ſpecial skill prove current, feaſible, laudable, and profitable to a Common-wealth, then if one of twenty ſuch proffers did thrive effectually and proſperouſly, the trouble of Settlement was recompenſed more than an hundred times treble; yet this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers deſigns being many, and ſeveral, and alſo viſible and perfect, to the eyes of ſence, and ears of underſtanding, and as freely proffered without any coſt as can be expected, have been retarded in the ſetling, by the means of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:133314:6"/> as have, and will, if they may be permitted and believed, ſtill endeavour to ſtupifie the ears of Authority with falſe pleadings, to the great loſſe and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of the people, and inſtead thereof gain the Nation a diſgrace, being a rhing very unreaſonable and ſhameful.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe Emblems of the ſeditious and ſpightful blaſters of the bloſſoms and flowers of welfare, will not abate their croſſe reſolutions,<note place="margin">A caution not to regard ſuch Calumniators.</note> then may they range where they pleaſe, and ſow tares where they liſt, provided that your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours will vouchſafe, to make it one of your principal buſineſſes to ſuperviſe the laborious works and producements of the Propoſer, with more eager conſpicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than formerly, and then he is confident your Honours ſhall find his perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, to be a ſufficient antidote againſt the putrified Air of thoſe, by whoſe breath tares (as aforeſaid) and other weeds and land impediments would be continued and increaſed, if your Honours prevent it not,<note place="margin">The Propoſer ſtands upon his credit and reputation in juſtification of his buſineſſe. ☜</note> and take hold of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and contemn ſuch peeviſh Criticks, in owning theſe propoſals as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick buſineſs of Parliament, whoſe profitable effects to the Nation may well ſupport it with the true title of the ſame, although the Propoſer will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude himſelf, and the name of <hi>Duckets,</hi> of that Honour and ſhare that the Laws of God and Man affords them, which muſt be ſo if he would complie with an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> to himſelf and Friend, in diſclaiming a moderate ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which no way can ariſe unto him and them by any falſe, uncouth, ſiniſter, deluſion or evaſion, as will preſently be made manifeſt for ſatisfaction of your Honours, and for calming the boyſterous tempeſtuous winds of all that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, needie, greedy or factious, unleſs (the Author of all miſchief) be in it.</p>
            <p>Certainly all oppoſites (though never ſo ill minded to others) would gladly have payment for any goods they ſell, and reciprocal returns for civilities,<note place="margin">Every man will look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Reward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h ſell, or doe for any man.</note> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Friendſhips, with a full recompence for any good ſervice, if they be of a capacity in any of theſe (as ſeldom they are) and according to that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer doth but expect to be reſpected with ſome little and mean requital, farr beneath the deſert of his great ſervice to the Commonwealth, in which Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings no man can be jealous of any falſhood, whereby he might delude, and draw the Nation to raiſe him a profit farr tranſcending the benefit of his diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries during the fourteen years; for if his deſigns are of little conſequence, ſmall profit, and hardly of any uſe, then hath he with diſgrace loſt all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, and charge, yet none but himſelf damnifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. And if they prove mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately profitable, and proſperouſly worthy of uſe,<note place="margin">The Propoſers reward will be according to the merit of his deſigns.</note> and of ſome ſufficient be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, then will the ſhape, ſize, and quantity of his reward be ſuitable according to the beneficial aſſiſtance the Weal-publick receiveth. But if his deſigned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries ſhould prove to be of a moſt vaſt valew in additional honour to your Honours, and a wealthy proſperity to the Commonwealth, then by a true rule of proportion, a fair and fitting well-deſerved honour,<note place="margin">If his deſigns prove ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and good his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</note> and large recompence the Propoſer doth conceive himſelf (againſt the World) to be a meritorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of. And if the numerous ſmall compoſitions for Licences from all that make uſe of his diſcoveries ſhould ariſe to great ſums or Mulcts, yet in deſpight of contradiction the performer is a well deſerving owner thereof, and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs will ſhew himſelf as able in diſtribution of what he hath gained, upon chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table good wayes and uſes,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as he was induſtrious in atchieving and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poſſeſſion of the ſame; for who doth know but that he is naturally ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted unto the relief of the poorer ſort, and the practice of laudable actions
<pb facs="tcp:133314:7"/> therewith in ſome eminent degree of Religious pious charity, ſuch as may be as great a preſident in good works, and gratious liberality, as he hath been ſtudious in advancing welfare and plentie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A strange caſe that ſuch wealthy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns ſhould be retarded by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting ſelf-ended people. The Propoſer will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject himſelf to any diſgrace, to be a diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious perſons for the future. The P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opoſers good will to benefit his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrey demonſtrated by keeping ſo long his ſecrets undiſcovered to forein Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Propoſers ſtudies and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, why may not God bleſſe this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as well as others to breed a perſon of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable parts fit perpetually to be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed?</note>Is it not then ſtrange that upon theſe weak barres of perſons indigent in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, or the like incidences, or Epitomies of envy and wretchedneſſe as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſcribed, that the Propoſers deſignes might then be raiſed to the high name of a ſpecial publick buſineſſe, and not otherwiſe? This is very rigid in thoſe that would endeavour to have your Honours adhere therewith, but muſt neceſſarily be a great debaſing of the Propoſers diſcretion, and very much beneath any Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſt that hath atchieved to perfection in ſmaller myſteries, and therefore he cannot ſubmit to ſuch an ignominie, without a foul ſcorn and diſdain therein to be guilty, as alſo by ſuch actions to become a diſcourager of any Academick, or other ingenuous perſons, who in this, or enſuing ages, ſhall, or may attain unto eminent knowledge in the myſteries of nature, or the like.</p>
            <p>The P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opoſer hopeth, that he deſerveth better things than theſe intricacies of his native Countrey, in reference to his good intentions of their future proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as alſo his care of their honour, they being ſo dilatory in the ſettlement of their own welfare. Yet hath the Propoſer hitherto had the patience not to ſend his diſcoveries into any other Nation, although often ſolicited to that purpoſe by ſeveral agents of thoſe forein parts, that would have raiſed thereby their own riches, and advanced their pleaſure in farther laughter and deriſion at the people of this Nation, for ſlighting and letting paſſe the opportunity of every new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned enterprize.</p>
            <p>For it hath been noted, that many nations and territories of the world have produced ſome perſons of ſingularity in all arts, ſciences, faculties and callings, and all derived from the Meridian of invention; the which illuſtrious excellence of perſons renowned, have adorned moſt part of the univerſe with the ſplendent glitter of glorious diſcoveries, their names and qualities needing no recital; for that no intelligible perſon is ignorant of their particular excellence, in Wiſdome and Knowledge; and ſeeing that it hath pleaſed God to bleſs other parts of the world with meſſengers of tranſcendent gifts, why then ſhould <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be obnoxious to their own honour and profit in neglecting the employment of the Propoſer? whoſe intellectuals were ever naturally from the ſpring of his youth, addicted to the love of profitable rarities, and new inventions in the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orick part of Elements and temperaments, and the methods of practice, with as much willingneſs to enrich his native Countrey, in reſembling former founders of high and mighty things. Yet with all humble obedience in his ſubmiſſive ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, he hath aimed and endeavoured at knowledge, with as much ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs and eagerneſs as to his undertakings are recited, with as faithfull inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as any of thoſe ſurmounting perſons that acquired to much fame and glory to themſelves and their Native Countries. The which your honours may experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally know by making uſe of the Propoſer, who is able to fill up the room and places left void and barren, with the fulneſs of skill, and better advantage in husbandry, and other myſteries and manufactories which were left at too low a gage of perfection by former diſcoverers; the which may by vertue of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers care be more perfectly eſtabliſhed and ſetled, and thereby as he hath had place, liberty and room left him for ſuch performance that others could not do: ſo when he ſhall have perfected what hitherto hath been left undone in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, he certainly then ſhall juſtly merit a place of remembrance in thoſe liſts
<pb facs="tcp:133314:7"/> and rolls in which learned Authors and Hiſtorians have recorded the honour and dignity of former renowned Diſcoverers, the which preferment is one of the guerdons deſired by Naturaliſts, they having felicity in fame beyond the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Riches.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe motives of truth and reaſon may occaſion theſe humble motions to be in ſome convenient time diſpatched and ſetled,<note place="margin">The great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and profit which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract by a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſettlement of the premiſes.</note> then will your Honours be made famous with the glory of all thoſe proſperous agitations and deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, together with all ſort of ſatisfactions, which are at large deſcribed in this enſuing addreſſe; to the end that your Honours may be fully ſatisfied of thoſe rich land affairs, whoſe wealthy income will in many degrees ſurmount the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digency which this Nation is often incident unto; and the real aſſurance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will appear more evident by your Honours peruſal of this following deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, whereof this firſt part hath relation unto, which will in truth and reaſon outbear all miſconſtructions, ſordid ſuggeſtions and pretences, and all ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign Incendiaries, as do, as aforeſaid, endeavour to divert the laudable intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the moſt renowned Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">Any Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Member of Parliament may receive ample ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the premiſes in leſs than an houres time.</note> from ſettlement of any great and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good or benefit, which is like to enſue to the Commonwealth in general, and to the particular honour of thoſe who intend to be the chief promoters thereof, who may receive ample ſatisfaction by proof, as to Land, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental demonſtration as to Leather, arguments to oppoſition, and reſponſe to queries in all the aforeſaid paſſages in about an houres time, if cauſe there be that any Honourable Member require the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now the Propoſer having given a ſufficient account of his proceedings, humbly craveth your Honours favour to ſpare a ſmall time in peruſal of what is hereafter to be ſaid; which queſtionleſſe will induce as great a willingneſſe in all worthy Patriots to countenance, and further a ſpeedy ſettlement of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, for the benefit of their reſpective Countries, as was performed by his late Highneſſe <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector, and prudent Council, in their grant of Patents, as was before expreſsed. And by ſuch a ſettlement the Propoſer will be cleared of the Aſperſions of various cenſurers, who often make doubts and ſuggeſtions by reaſon of the Propoſers many expreſſions and writings, and that he hath been ſo long in performance of what he hath held forth;<note place="margin">Reaſons why there hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been no performance of what is held forth.</note> not conſidering that it was divers Alterations in State, Barrs in Old Lawes, Mortality of ſome gratious Friends to good works, Sickneſs in the Propoſer, and ſundry other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinations, which hindred and delayed the proſecution, and actual perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the premiſes, and not any failing, or diſability in the Propoſer, who hath followed his agitations with ſo much eagerneſs, that it hath ſtirred up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny detractors, who out of envy to ſuch high undertakings, breath out trifling ſuſurrations againſt the Propoſers perſon and undertakings;<note place="margin">Depravers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note> and others ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious not to be outſtript in Ingenuity, or to ſee another mans increaſe of honour, expreſs and caſt forth ſtrange, and uncouth prevarications, with private emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that if not diſcerned, might corrode the hold this Nation might take of this preſent opportunity, in advancing their greater plenty, which they themſelves might live to ſee, after authority is granted to the Propoſer, and other Nations prevented in their hope of <hi>Englands</hi> declination thereof, as they have formerly done <hi>Columbus,</hi> and many other Miniſters of profit, which in this caſe would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more ſtrange, for that the charge of acting, performing, publiſhing,<note place="margin">☜</note> and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving poſſeſſion of the premiſes, will come clear to the Nation, without the coſt of one penny, and the charge incident to the ſettlement will be very little:
<pb facs="tcp:133314:8"/> and moreover the Propoſer will carry on his deſignes and undertakings, until they be clearly diſcovered, at his own charge; for he ſtands upon the points of his reputation, and juſt meaning in theſe particulars, and all others, as he hath done all his life time,<note place="margin">The Propoſer renounces all bye ends or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, other than a legal ſettlement.</note> (if not miſtaken) and renounces all benefit from any perſon in the world, in reference to his undertakings, with as much deteſtation as is proper to the moſt worthy Obliging perſon in the world, or any favour, other than that Law of fourteen yeares privilege, for the Exerciſe of his Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as is peculiar in ſuch Caſes, for the incouragement of all thoſe who by their Studies and Endeavours, have attained unto high and laudable diſcoveries in Elemental myſteries.</p>
            <p>And as much as lies in the power of the Propoſer, touching himſelf and his deſigns, the people of this Nation ſhall not be guilty of the firſt preſident of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, and ſuppreſſion of any flouriſhing proſperity, which might illuſtrate the glory of this and other Nations: Therefore God forbid that the arguments of ſelf-ended and detracting perſons, or any ſuch that want parts to underſtand Myſteries; or vulgar wits, that love old cuſtomes or dull actions, more than profit; or ſpleeny Cynicks, who will ſpeak againſt all things, and like nothing but what they do themſelves; or any ſuch oppoſites, who may now make it their buſineſſe to obſtruct the Propoſers proceedings;<note place="margin">What miſchief Depravers may do in a Nation.</note> ſhould divert, and prevail with your Honours, to let ſuch an Emolument and Ornament of a Nation fall to the ground; eſpecially conſidering that Store can be no Sore, and that there is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient need for profitable ſupply, and no want of lawfull power of prudent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; and under favour of your Honours, no lack of ſerenity or ability in the Propoſer, to give his Native Country the firſt Livery and Seiſin of thoſe rich in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, wherewith he is indued. Neither are there any barres in Law, or any obſtacles to blind the Nation from the lively view thereof, but only the damp and foggy air ariſing from dulneſs, or the dark clouds of brow-bent malice, or the faithleſſe, fruitleſſe blaſtings of incredulity, or ſuch like ill-aſpected motions; unleſſe that any ſuch barking and bawling depravers, can face to face, before the Honourable Members of Parliament, diſprove, or make appear any thing againſt the faithfull Integrity, Skill, Knowledge, Perſon, Parts or Undertakings of the Propoſer: but if ſuch perſons ſhall not ground their oppoſition on Truth and Reaſon, but think to bear it out with a liberty derived from falſhood and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, they will find themſelves deceived, and in danger to runne the hazard of bringing a laſting diſgrace and <hi>Odium</hi> upon themſelves,<note place="margin">The Propoſers defiance to ſuch Depravers.</note> for unworthily endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to obſtruct and hinder the increaſe of ſuch honour and fertility, as might be advanced to the enriching of your Honours Treaſury, and the Commonwealths future happineſſe and proſperity. And by this means the expectation of all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſons, may be ſatisfied; the Peſt of envy, antidoted; the Author, and all other perſons ſtudious in good works, encouraged; your Honours, eternally magnified; and this our Air and Climate purged of all the contagious infections of Spirits Malevolent to high and worthy principles; wherein they have not abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of apprehenſion to diſcern the various myſteries of Nature, which the vaſt world plentifully affordeth unto all thoſe who are ſerious Obſervers of her Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Deity, and diligent Searchers into the Multiplicity of her Natural Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Cauſes, with her other Contingencies: which the Propoſer all his life time having been ſtudious, and converſant in, hath attained to the knowledge and perfection, chiefly of theſe enſuing Deſignes, and many others not herein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: which if hereafter entertained and ſettled, may as well as the reſt, be very advantagious to the Commonwealth.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:133314:8"/>
               <head>The particular Heads of which Inventions, contained in the Bills aforementioned, for the Improvement of all ſorts of Land and Leather, are as followeth;</head>
               <p>FIrſt, The ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> undertaketh to take away for ever,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Propoſers undertakings for Land. To deſtroy all manner of Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh.</note> the greateſt part of the prejudice and damage which is cauſed in Land, of ſeveral ſorts, by reaſon of Heath or Ling, Fearn or Brakes, Ruſhes, Sedges, Reeds, Thiſtles, Nettles, Moſſe, Broom, Furze or Gorſe, Brambles, Bryers, Blackthorns, and other Incumbrances, deſtructive to the growth and goodneſſe of Corn and Graſſe, or prejudicial and hurtful to Paſture, Meadow, and arable Lands.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To improve, and inrich the value and goodneſſe of Land,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> To improve Shallow Soil.</note> where the Turf is ſhallow by reaſon of Gravel, Sand, Rock, Clunch or Chalk, lying too near the Superficies of the Earth, that there is not a ſufficient depth of Soyl to be plowed; ſo that it is altogether unprofitable Land for Corn, neither will it bear any conſiderable quantity of Graſſe. The which Improvement is and may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, without the uſual great charge and paines of carrying Lime or Dung of Cattel upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, To keep a great part of all hilly, dry, riſing grounds, by water,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> To keep moiſt hilly dry grounds.</note> more moiſt and fertile; not with any great chargeable Engines, Leaden Pipes, Pumps, or any ſort of Mills or Water houſes, or any new way now in practice, or held forth; but by ways &amp; means ſlight, cheap and eaſie, by ordering of Lands in various ſhapes, figures, and proportions, for compaſſing, and gainecoping the drift and courſe of Waters; and by Engines and Inſtruments of ſmall value, from five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings price, unto five pounds and upwards, portable for either man, horſe, or cart, according to their ſeveral ſizes, as the depth of the water, and the height of the ground ſhall require; which will carry up, and gain advantage of waters ſo much, as thereby Lands may be ſoakned, and kept more moiſt and fertile, and dry places in Summer may be ſupplyed with water.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, To make a ſort of rich Soyl fit for Agriculture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> To fertilize Land with a new Manure.</note> and Manuring of ground, much of the nature and effects of Lime, or Dung of Cattel, where Lime or Dung of Cattel is ſcarce, and is to be performed with ſmall charge and paines.</p>
               <p>ANd alſo the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> undertaketh, (whereas Bark of Oaks, Aſh,<note place="margin">The Propoſers undertakings for Leather. ☜</note> Sumack, Galls, Salt and Allom, being the principal ingredients now uſed in Tannage, are very ſcarce and dear, and likewiſe harſh and corroſive) To diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and teach all Tradeſmen as to Leather, a profound Art and Myſtery, never before practiſed in this Commonwealth;</p>
               <p>Firſt, to make Leather without any the Liquors or Ingredients now in uſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> To tanne Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without Bark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> in ſhorter time, and with leſſe charge, far to exceed all former Tannage, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Grain and Colour; and more laſting, firm and ſubſtantial, fit for all manner of ſervice, according to the nature, ſizes, and degrees of the hides and skins ſo Tanned and Tawed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If any Tradeſman as to Leather, be deſirous for cuſtome ſake, or ſome other private ends or reaſons, ſtill to make uſe of Bark, or any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients,
<pb facs="tcp:133314:9"/> now in practice;<note place="margin">To make Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by mixing his new Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients with the old.</note> The Liquors and Ingredients invented and found out by the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket,</hi> are of ſuch virtue and quality, that if by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections ſome of them be mixed and compounded with the former uſed Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients, they will make farr better Leather, and in ſhorter time, than is, or can be made, by the only and ſingle uſe of Bark, Sumack, or any other Ingredients now in common practice, and the harſh and corroſive qualities of the old Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, will be very much diverted and abated by mixture of the new.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> will diſcover Liquors of ſuch rare perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that will clarify and prepare all ſorts of raw Hides and Skins, for more ſpeedy and better Tannage; Either in Liquors and Ingredients of his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention; Or in Liquors of his own mixed and compounded with thoſe former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed;<note place="margin">To prepare raw Hides and Skins for more ſpeedy and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Tannage.</note> Or in Liquors made with Barke, Sumack, and the reſt now in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practice; And further the ſaid Liquors are of ſuch influence, that they will relax and ſoften the Natural hardneſſe in raw Hides and Skins, and cauſe the Callus and Gelly in them, to be more expeditiouſly digeſted in the Tanning or Tawing; And moreover the ſaid Liquors will prevent the putrifaction inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to great Hides intended for Soal Leather, for the Tanners by Stifeling them on great heaps cloſe together, do taint and periſh them on the Grayn ſide, with a rottenneſſe, as is apparent by the eaſy cracking of them if forced or bended.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Propoſer undertakes to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcover his new Arts.</note>A l which ſaid Arts, Myſteries, Secrets, and Inventions, both for Improvement of Land and Leather, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> undertaketh to make known in print or otherwiſe, for the publique good of this Common-wealth, and to direct and teach the method, uſe, and practice of them.</p>
               <p>The real performance of which Inventions, are ſufficiently atteſted, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as aforeſaid, and need not ſo great Evidence, but that any rational perſon will Conceive that the undertaker is well verſed in the Myſteries of Nature, and able to perform many rarities of skill and knowledge for the Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Land;<note place="margin">☞</note> ſeeing that by his ſtudy in Natures Operation, hee hath attained unto the whole ſcope and body, of the Science and Myſtery, for converting all ſorts of raw Hides and Skins into Leather, beyond all expectation and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, as is actually made apparent, for that the make thereof, tranſcends in ſuch a degree of goodneſſe, all former Tannage, as never was performed, or accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, by the moſt profound Ingenuities of this or former Ages; And it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that much Land continueth ſterril and barren, for want of help to aſſiſt Nature, Land holders and Land-owners having been hitherto as Stupid and Negligent in Improvements, as Tanners and others were in Improvement of Leather.</p>
               <p>And if there may be now a ſpeedy ſettlement of the premiſes, it will be an Extraordinary help and benefit to all Tanners,<note place="margin">A preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency for Tanners.</note> and other Tradeſmen as to Leather, who will thereby ſave great Charge and paines, which otherwiſe they muſt be at in ſeeking for <hi>Bark;</hi> and other Ingredients, to furniſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves withall, which are both Scarce and Coſtly.</p>
               <p>That therefore the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> in recompence of his great charge and paines, and love to his Native Country, and for the incouragement of all ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Artiſts for the future, may be impowred to have the Sole exerciſe and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his ſaid Inventions,<note place="margin">Grant of Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement.</note> for improvement of Land and Leather, for fowerteen years, according to the Laws and Statutes of this and other civil Nations.</p>
               <p>And may have power and authority during the ſaid Term, to grant Licences
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133314:9"/> to all perſons within the three Nations and the Dominions thereto belonging,<note place="margin">Humble moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental reaſons why there can be no good ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſufficient penalties.</note> to practiſe his ſaid inventions, which are new, and never before in preſent or frequent occupation, in the ſame Method, Form, and Manner, with ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and alterations; And although the benefit of them be never ſo great, yet no man is compelled as in ſuch caſes in other Nations, to make uſe of any of the ſaid Inventions, but left at will and pleaſure to be Pilots to their own wills.</p>
               <p>And theſe rich deſigns aforementioned,<note place="margin">☜</note> which may ſo much advance the Commonwealth, being the Rights, and due Treaſure of the Propoſer, and no-other perſon having an intereſt and property in them, but himſelf;<note place="margin">Theſe Reaſons why the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ought to have good pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties are not included in the Bills.</note> that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all Equity and Reaſon, it is requiſite for him by way of Treaty with the honourable Members, humbly to lay claim to ſome fitting aſſurance, and ſquare and legal conditions, thereby to be certain of ſome reaſonable ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for thoſe wealthy benefits, which are by him to be preſented to thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are concerned to make uſe of them, and therefore in all Right and Equity, your Honours cannot but grant him ſuch a power, as is congruent and incident to any venturers, who have uſed great induſtry, and ſpent their beſt times and fortunes in bringing from forein parts of the World into their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, ſome enriching Merchandize, at which time the Owners there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are at liberty to make their own conditions, with thoſe they furniſh; and therefore accordingly that the Propoſer may not be defeated of the honour and reward which ought juſtly to accrue to him, for his new Inventions, which are of farr greater value than any kind of Merchandize, and made ridiculous to the diſcouragement of ingenious Artiſts for the future, and this Nation ſubject to the evil effects of ingratitude, and likewiſe this Act made invalid by evill-minded perſons, who although their compoſition for Licences, will be little or nothing in compariſon of their benefit; yet moſt people are of ſuch perverſe and ill-diſpoſed natures, that they will rather indeavour deceitful practices, than be conformable to the Laws; Therefore to prevent ſuch fallacious people, and that his recompence and ſatisfaction, for his great Charge, Study, and pains, may be anſwerable to his Merits and Deſerts, and that he may have a ſecure Title, the Propoſer under your Honours favour, by way of civil bargain,<note place="margin">Why the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ought to be ſo great.</note> doth humbly lay claim to ſuch good penalties, as are hereafter to be named, wherein there cannot be a wrong or prejudice to any that mean well, for that all good-minded people, will not make uſe of the Propoſers skill without due Licence, and therefore regard not penalties be they never ſo great, and thoſe who are of ſmall ability will never run the hazard of them, and moreover thoſe perſons who are unjuſtly and fraudulently intended, may be better ordered and ſubdued with fear of good penalties, for it will ſuit with your Honours pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and wiſdome, that thoſe perſons who regard nor fear either Laws or Honeſty, but wilfully contemn and break them, ſhould be ſeverely puniſhed, and largely ſuffer; for the uſe of Iuſtice, will be prevented by a well ſetled Juſtice.</p>
               <p>And therefore that the penalty of forty ſhillings may be impoſed upon all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, for every Acre of Land, whereon they ſhall without Licence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133314:10"/> firſt had and obteined from the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> or his Aſſigns,<note place="margin">Penalties for Land.</note> uſe or pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſe any of his wayes, means, methods, or directions, for the improvement of Paſture, Meadow, and arable grounds, in any of the particulars aforeſaid; And alſo the Sum of twenty ſhillings, upon every Acre of Land, for every years continuing the uſe of them (without Licence) after Conviction; And alſo that the penalty of twenty pounds, may be impoſed upon all perſons that ſhall make uſe, or exerciſe (without Licence) any of his Engines, to carry up wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to any Cities, Towns, Villages, particular Houſes, or any other places whatſoever, other than for Improvement of hilly dry grounds in manner as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; And twenty ſhillings for every days continuing the uſe of them (without Licence) after Conviction.</p>
               <p>And moreover to prevent unjuſt and indirect practices by Tanners, that the penalty of one hundred pounds, may be impoſed upon any Tanner, or other perſon, that ſhall (without Licence firſt had and obteined from the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> or his Aſſigns) make,<note place="margin">Penalties for Leather.</note> uſe, or practiſe, all or any part of his wayes, means, directions, Liquors, or Ingredients for the Tanning, Tawing, or preparing of Leather as aforeſaid; And forty ſhillings for every dayes continuing the uſe of them (without Licence) after the firſt Conviction.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ought to be recovered.</note>And that the Offenders in any the premiſſes aforeſaid may upon Oath of two Witneſſes, before one or two Juſtices of the Peace be Convicted.</p>
               <p>And that all Juſtices of the Peace, may be impowred and required upon ſuch Conviction, to iſſue out their Warrants to the Conſtables of the place where the Offenders live, for the levying by diſtreſſe, the aforeſaid penalties.</p>
               <p>And that no perſon whatſoever (may without Licence as aforeſaid) alter, Counterfeit, Change, or falſify, either by addition to, or ſubſtraction from the ſame,<note place="margin">No falſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders or Counterfeitors.</note> or other alteration, all or any the aforeſaid Inventions, Engines, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, or other utenſils, Manure, Liquors, or Ingredients, either for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Land or Leather as aforeſaid, thereby to pretend him or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to be the Inventors or Deviſors thereof, upon pain of the forfeitures and payments aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>That whereas Printers, Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioners, Bookſellers, and other perſons, may by falſe and counterfeit Books and Copies very much wrong and prejudice,<note place="margin">Penalties for Printers, &amp;c.</note> not only the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket,</hi> but likewiſe the Commonwealth; That to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch inconveniences, which may thereby ariſe, a good penalty to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of one thouſand pounds, may be impoſed upon them, for printing or putting to ſale (without Licence) any of his Books or Copies of Directions, either for improvement of Land in any the particulars aforeſaid; Or for Tanning, Tawing,<note place="margin">To be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Action of Debt.</note> or preparing of Leather as aforeſaid; And alſo to forfeit five pounds for every Book or Copy of direction, which they ſhall print or expoſe to ſale, after the firſt Diſcovery and Conviction; And the ſaid penalties to be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Action of Debt in any Court of Record in the three Nations, where no eſſoyn or wager of Law ſhall be admitted or allowed them.</p>
               <p>And that the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> or his Aſſigns, may by warrant from a Juſtice of the Peace,<note place="margin">Liberty to make ſearch in caſe of ſuſpition for diſcovery of Offenders.</note> to a Conſtable or other Officer, make ſearch for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of ſuch perſons, as they ſhall ſuſpect to make uſe of any of his Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, either for improvement of Land, or Leather, (without Licence as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.)</p>
               <p>That all the penalties and forfeitures aforeſaid, are to be divided into three
<pb facs="tcp:133314:10"/> equal parts, one third part to your Honours, to be paid into the Exchequer,<note place="margin">Penalties di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to three parts.</note> one other third part thereof, to be to the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket</hi> or his Aſſigns, and the other third part to the Informer.</p>
               <p>And now your Honours having heard,<note place="margin">Alluding his Inventions to Merchandary commodities as a rational inducement though no part of the Bill. The ſmall and reaſonable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer expects for his diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries.</note> what penalties have been humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, with Reaſons why they ought to be ſo great, yee will bethink with your ſelves, what ſatisfaction and reward, it is fit for the Propoſer to expect, and in this caſe to ſatisfie your Honours, the Propoſer doth not intend, that his recompence and gain, ſhall compare with a Venturer, or Merchant, that brings in Gold, Silver, Bullion, pretious Stones, or Jewels, to grace, pleaſure, adorn, and inrich a Nation, who will not part with their Commodities, unleſſe at very dear rates, or the full worth of them; But the Propoſer intends not by many degrees to be ſo coſtly, to the receivers of the profit, which thoſe whom he hath to deal withall will receive; for although not only the preſent profit, but likewiſe the perpetual good and benefit, which will ariſe, by a comparative rule of proportion, will be extraordinary great, yet the owner of theſe riches will expect from each particular perſon, that ſhall by vertue of a Licence, have the benefit of his Treaſure, little more mony from firſt to laſt of his authority, than the Baggs, Caſes, Cheſts, Veſſels, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of outſides, wherein thoſe rich commodities were incloſed and conteined, and then afterwards all people, are to have both outſides and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and all rights and privilege to his Diſcoveries and Inventions, be they never ſo rich, and profitable, without any payment or acknowledgement, and ſo to continue to this and after ages for perpetuity.</p>
               <p>That no Juſtice of the peace or other Officer, ſhall be ſued, or prejudiced,<note place="margin">No Officers to be prejudiced for what they ſhall do in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the ſaid Acts. That the ſaid Acts may be good and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any former Acts or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</note> for what they ſhall doe, in perſuance and execution of the ſaid Acts.</p>
               <p>That the ſaid Acts both for improvement of Land and Leather, may be good and effectual, in all Courts of Juſtice to the benefit of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket,</hi> Notwithſtanding the Statute made in the firſt year of the reign of King <hi>James,</hi> touching the duty of Tanners, Curriers, Shooemakers, and other cutters of Leather; Or any imperfection in the ſaid Acts; Or any former Act, Statute, matter, or thing, concerning either Lind or Leather, to the contrary in any wiſe Notwithſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Breviats of the forementioned Bills, and ſome other matters inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them, being ſet forth, the Propoſer doth prepare theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anſwers to ſome objections that have, and may be made by Covetous, Malevolent perſons.</head>
               <p>ANd firſt whereas it may be objected by ſome croſs people,<note place="margin">Several Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered as to Land.</note> that improvement of Land, will neceſſarily induce ſuch a plenty of all things, as will cauſe a general cheapneſſe, and abate the price of all commodities, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence diminiſh the Rent of Lands, and the revenues of Noblemen, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, by diſabling the Tenant to pay his rent (to this it may be anſwered.)</p>
               <p>That this Objection proceeds from a Root of private intereſt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>1</label> 
                  <note place="margin">"Anſwer.</note> and reſpects only the profits of particular perſons, and thoſe who are againſt improvements are Enemies to the Commonwealth where they live, for improvements do
<pb facs="tcp:133314:11"/> not impoveriſh, but inrich a Commonwealth, for theſe following reaſons;</p>
               <p>Firſt although Land be improved, that it bear more Corn and Graſſe than before, and that plenty thereupon cauſeth cheapneſs; yet the quantity being much more will make that good again and out-bear the cheapneſſe;<note place="margin">☞</note> that there needs no abatement of Rents, for Land will for the moſt part receive an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement,<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> abatement of Rents by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements.</note> proportionable to the value and goodneſs that it is now of, as for example, if the improvement be to a third part of the value of the Land, then Land of two ſhillings an Acre will be improved to be as good as Land of three ſhillings an Acre; Land of twenty ſhillings an Acre to be as good as Land of thirty ſhillings an Acre, and ſo in proportion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>2</label> Secondly, by improvement a leſſe quantity of Land, will ſerve for Corn, and may be ſowen with Hemp,<note place="margin">More Land may be ſpared for ſeveral uſes</note> Flax, Cole-ſeed, Rape-ſeed, woad or madder, which will increaſe a manufacture, and produce an improvement, and mantainance for innumerable poor people.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, more Land may be laid down for Paſture, for maintaining milch Kine,<note place="margin">More Land for Paſture then formerly.</note> for plenty of Butter and Cheeſe, to relive the poor, and for tranſportation beyond the ſeas, and likewiſe to breed and mantain great Cattel for proviſions for the Land, and Navy at ſea, and for the encreaſe of that ſtaple commodity of Leather; and alſo to breed and maintain ſheep for the increaſe of that other Staple commodity of Wool, for the making of Cloaths and Stuffs, and other commodities; not only for the uſe of this Commonwealth, but for Tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and maintaining innumerable poor people on work.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, By improvement of Land, a far greater plenty of Corn, Cattel, and all ſorts of proviſions for Food and Rayment,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> A far greater pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y will be raiſed.</note> will be raiſed in this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, inſomuch that it may be a Storehouſe of plenty for perpetuity, and have ſo great an overplus of Food and Rayment, as that it may ſupply and help the wants of Forein Nations, and ſo bring vaſt ſummes of money, honour and profit to this Commonwealth, and yet have at home ſuch a fulneſſe of plenty, as that the Act for Tranſportation, made by a late Parliament, may rather be inlarged than abrogated, as now it is in part, ſeveral commodities exceeding the Rates in that Act limited and appointed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> Anſwer. <note place="margin">Rents rather increaſed than leſſened.</note>Laſtly, no mans Incomes or Revenues will be leſſe, by reaſon of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, but rather bettered, for their cauſe of expence in ſuch a plenty will be leſſened, and they will have all manner of proviſions and home-bred commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities at very cheap rates.</p>
               <p>And if fertile bottomes are not better than barren mountains, and if the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Fruits of the Earth, are not beſide a bleſſing, a great ſupport and eſtabliſhment of the policy of a Nation, then why do the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge ſuch privileges to arable Lands beyond Paſture? What mean the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes to reſtrain the converting of arable Lands into paſture grounds, to the hindrance of Tillage? Why are all Heath and other barren grounds exempt from the payment of Tythes, the firſt ſeven yeares after improvement, by a peculiar privilege?</p>
               <p>Beſides, Improvements are very advantageous for hoſpitality, and relief of the poor,<note place="margin">A general bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</note> in ſetting Old and Young, and all idle perſons, to ſome ſlight work, who can endure no hard Labour, and ſo there will be no wandring poor as now, nor any to be relieved, but lame and blind perſons, which will be very great honour and profit to this Common-wealth; for that Nation is moſt honoured, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, by foreiners, wherein is the moſt fertility and ingenuity.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:133314:11"/>
               <p>But if there be any who are not ſenſible of the bleſſing and advantage of plenty, queſtionleſſe it were fit that ſuch perſons would confine themſelves, for ſome years, to inhabit upon the tops of ſome barren Hills, or Mountains, to make tryal of ſuch proviſions, as Nature there affordeth,<note place="margin">☜</note> without the help of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and there to learn by experience, the truth of theſe aſſertions, rather than to be convinced by the ſtrength of argument in a plentifull Country, where perhaps the fullneſſe of their ſtomacks may dull the acuteneſſe of their apprehenſions.</p>
               <p>And for a further ſatisfaction of what hath been before expreſſed,<note place="margin">Several Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctions anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Leather.</note> and now eſpecially concerning that ſtaple commodity of Leather.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that all Leather made by the new Art, and Invention, of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Ducket,</hi> will in all degrees of perfection, ſo far exceed all former Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, that a great trade may be raiſed in this Common-wealth, by that Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity; for in what Nation ſoever, any new Art, or profitable Science,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> ☜ That Nation where this new Art is firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered will receive the greateſt benefit.</note> is firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and found out, that Nation will for many yeares after, have the ſole trade, and benefit therof, and all Nations will addreſſe themſelves thither, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving there will be the beſt made, where it was firſt invented; and the chief parts of this new Art participating of rare Myſteries, and neat and private practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet are cheap and eaſy to be performed without the plain and common drudgery now uſed in Tannage, and may be ſo diſpoſed of by the Propoſor in this or other Nations, that during many ſcore years, no other part of the world may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any knowledge or benefit thereof.<note place="margin">And may keep the ſaid new Art a long time ſecret amongſt themſelves.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which grounds, how happy may this Nation be, in the ſpeedy ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe Myſteries and Inventions? for the ſaid Science may be many years here kept amongſt our ſelves, and Forein Nations induced to import their raw Hides and Skins, into this Common-wealth, to be converted into Leather after the ſaid new Art; Or if we pleaſe, the ſaid accompliſhing ingredients may be ſold,<note place="margin">The Leather by reaſon of its goodneſſe may be tranſported into other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> and tranſported at very good rates, into other Countries, where they are not found; for Leather converted after the ſaid new Art, will be of ſuch laſting wear and goodneſſe, that a third part thereof may be ſpared and ſold beyond the ſeas, at double or treble the price that now it is, and yet here amongſt our ſelves, it may be afforded at a more cheap and reaſonable rate than now is ſold at.</p>
               <p>And the ingredients, to prepare the ſaid liquors,<note place="margin">The new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients cheap and eaſie to be found.</note> are moſt of them to be had within this Common-wealth, at cheaper rates, than the aforeſaid old uſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, and will be of good benefit to the owners of the Grounds and Lands, where the ſaid ingredients are found.</p>
               <p>Secondly, whereas Tanners are commonly a whole year,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> ☜ More ſpeedy Tannage and a quicker re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</note> three quarters of a year, half a year, and the like, in Tannage, according to the ſizes of the Hides, and Skinns, they may hereafter by the uſe and practice of the inventers directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, make far better Leather, and in ſhorter time, whereby a quick return may be made thereof, which is the only advantage of a manufacture.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, although Bark of Oaks, and ſome other ingredients,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Bark and the Ingredients now uſed are harſh and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive. ☜</note> now principaly uſed in Tannage are very ſcarce, and coſtly; yet by their harſh corroſiveneſſe, they do very much periſh and deſtroy the ſtability and faſtneſſe of all raw Hides and Skins, (which in themſelves are ſome of the wonders of Nature in ſtrength and tough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) and thereby Leather is much weakned of its natural force, and no remedy was ever known for the ſame before this preſent time.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that Bark of Oakes, and other ingredients uſed by Tanners,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> The Trade of Tannage like to fail for want</note> are of ſuch high price and ſcarcity, that by means thereof, there is very much bad Leather made in in all parts of the three Nations, for want of full and perfect Tannage; And the ſaid trade is like within few ages, to be neer exti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uiſh'd by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:133314:12"/> Bark is like to be far more ſcarce, than now it is, if not in proceſſe of time quite conſumed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Timber is fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble times for the uſe of Bark.</note>Fiftly, the neceſſity of the uſe of the aforeſaid Bark is ſo great, that the Laws com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the owners of timber to fell and cut down the ſame, at unſeaſonable times, when the ſap is in it, which makes the timber ſo much worſe in price and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as the rate of Bark doth amount unto, and their loſſe in the Bark, will in great Families be countervailed in the goodneſſe, and laſting wear of the Leather made after the ſaid new Art.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſcarcity of Bark is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of much young wood.</note>Sixtly, that in this time of dearth, and ſcarcity of Bark, Tanners are ſo neceſſitous thereof, that by giving great prices for the ſame, they do thereby tempt, and procure the owners of groves and copſes, to make ſale of the ſame, when it is of very young growth, which if it were not to ſupply the Tanners in reference and and recompence of their high prices, the owners of many ſuch groves and copſes would permit and ſuffer the growth of them to continue, untill they came to be very good Timber, to ſerve either themſelves or their poſterity.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7.</hi> The ſale of Bark may not be utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, for ſeveral Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note>Seaventhly, the ſale of Bark of Aſh and ſome other ingredients, now in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, will not be utterly extinguiſhed, for theſe reaſons following; Firſt, by the mixing and compounding the liquors and ingredients, now in Common uſe, with his new prepared liquors and ingredients, will take away the corroſive quality of the old, and make moſt exquiſite Leather; Secondly, in ſome parts of the three Nations, the new ingredients may be ſcarce to be found, and the other ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents very plentifull; And Thirdly, ſome Engliſh people are affected very much with the diſpoſition of their neighbour Iriſh, and are altogether fond of old cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes, being a thing, whereunto vulgar capacities are much addicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for fear of future diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters.</note>Laſtly, theſe deſigns of ſo great conſequence, which are now in being, and are ſo freely tendred for the good of the Commonwealth, may in all likelyhood, by mortalitie, and other diſaſters (if not ſpeedily embraced by the Supream Rulers) be as long hid from this Common-wealth, as it hath before wanted it, for none do know, but that after ages may be as long deſtitute of ſuch an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, as former ages have been deficient of it.</p>
               <p>And now the Propoſer hopes, having cleared all objections, with theſe ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying reaſons, that now he hath no oppoſite to anſwer, unleſſe it be ſome particular perſons concern'd in the ſale of Bark, and the quick wearing out of ill Tann'd Leather, who reſpect their own private intereſt, more than the generall good of the Common-wealth, and ſuch as thoſe, he can divert and croſſe by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wayes, (if they ſhould endeavour to hinder a ſettlement of the premiſſes) with this one aſſertion, that it lyeth in the power of the Propoſer to diſcover and make known theſe his ſecrets in ſome induſtrious Forein Nation, who being thereby skilfully enabled in that maſter-piece of knowledge, will attract unto themſelves ſo high a degree of perfection,<note place="margin">A defeat to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and Malevolent Spirits.</note> in the ſaid Art and Myſtery, as will highly advance a manufacture there, and ſo much diminiſh the progreſſe thereof in theſe parts, as will occaſion Bark to ſell at as low a rate, as if the Propoſers directions, were here in frequent action: for all Leather made by the ſaid new Art, will be of ſuch laſting wear and goodneſſe, that it will be moſt in requeſt, and this Nation will altogether make uſe thereof, and be ſupplyed with the ſame, and ſo ſuch malevolent perſons may be defeated of their covetous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and this Nation attract loſſe, and diſgrace for their incredulitie, and other contempts againſt flouriſhing plenty, and other Nations gain the honour and profit, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ours, if not obvious to their own good, might have enjoyed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb facs="tcp:133314:12"/>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>ANd whereas it is before apparent, that the Liquors, and Ingredients, now uſed in Tannage, are corroſive and deſtructive unto all ſorts of Leather; So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe your Honours may be pleaſed to take notice of the great loſſe and prejudice this Nation doth ſuffer, in the dying of thoſe pretious Commodities of Silk and Wool into Blacks, which being in themſelves ſome of Natures rarities, are notwithſtanding ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much periſhed, and deſtroyed, for want of knowledge in Dyers, how to divert and qualify the inflaming and corroſive Natures of thoſe Ingredients, which they uſe in dying black, which prejudice and inconvenience, the Propoſer doth admire,<note place="margin">The prejudie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in dying of Blacks is e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to be preve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and addreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that the Naturalists of former Ages could not prevent, it being a thing ſo eaſy and open to the Propoſers skill and knowledge, although he doth not mention or promiſe perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof in the aforeſaid Bills, by reaſon if he ſhould, now with the reſt, tender his ſervice in another ſo material a buſineſs, he ſhould gain diſtaſt from the envious and unskilful in Natures Operations and Secrets, and ſhould unjustly be very much clamoured and repined at by many, for directing how to uphold and continue the full ſtrength and force of Wool and Silk in the dying, which would be great loſſe to the quickneſs of the Trade of Dyers, Silkmen, Drapers, Mercers, Taylors, and other Trades as to Silk and Wool: And although it is a buſineſs of ſmall difficulty, for the Propoſer to ſet forth a means of redreſſe, unto all Dyers, as well as Tanners, how to qualifie and divert the harſh and corroſive Natures of their now uſed Liquors and Ingredients, and to make all Silks and Woollen ſo dyed into black, to be as plump, ſoft, and ſtrong for laſting wear, as any other artificial colour; As alſo to ſtrike and permanently fix, thoſe ſtaining, fading, and decaying colours, both in Silk and Wool, which are dyed with Logwood, Brazil or the like, to continue in their freſh and lively Luſtre, unto the uttermost wear thereof, and yet without the help of that coſtly ingredient called Cutchoneal; And although this laſt clauſe,<note place="margin">Colours may be made more iluſtrious, fix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</note> concerning faſtning of colours in dying, be no great additional help to the Weal publique, yet it will be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect new Art of ſpecial good conſequence, in point of Reaſon and Ingenuity, to the Engliſh people; But the ſpoyling of the aforeſaid rich commodities, by dying them into Black, can be no other than a very unworthy practice, for that it is much loſſe to men, and queſtionleſſe an offence to God, eſpecially if it may be redreſſed; Yet <hi>England</hi> muſt loſe this Maſter-piece, unleſſe the Propoſer be deſired and encouraged thereunto, by the wiſe and prudent Magiſtrates of Parliament. And whereas the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have now ſome more honour and profit, beyond this or other Nations, in dying of Blacks, and preſerving the strength thereof, yet is not their skill in that particular, of ſo great and high a degree of perfection, but their Art may be ſo much exceeded by the Engliſh, as will remove the glory and profit which they attract from other Nations, unto this our Engliſh Continent, if the Magistrates thereof, in reſpect of their own welfare, do deſire to make uſe of the Induſtry of him, who truly honours all thoſe that love the flouriſhing proſperity of their Native Country, beyond others,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Ducket.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:13"/>
            <head>An Introduction to a Remarkeable Breviary in Verſes which are drawn in alluſion that this Nation may receive as much glory and wealthy preferment by the Induſtry and new Inventions of <hi>Thomas Ducket Eſq</hi> as other fortunate Nations have gained by imbracing the Diſcoveries of perſons famous in Knowledge and Action.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To the Worthy Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Having been a long time Servant to the Author of theſe enſuing Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Converſant in his Agitations, and now being imployed by him to attend the Impreſsion conteining ſeveral rarities of Nature by him brought to perfection for the advance of this Nation, and many other fignificant adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements to the high Court of Parliament concerning the ſtttlement of a glorious national preferment in honor and wealthineſſe, being Maſterpieces of that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence as they deſervedly merit the approbation of the Univerſe, called to mind a Poetical Berviarie of the ſaid <hi>Mr. Duckets</hi> undertakings, done by a Perſon of worth, being Fellow of a College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who having had experience of the ſaid <hi>Mr. Duckets</hi> abilities in many things as to Improvement of Land, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelf viewed, and had the Teſtimony of divers Tanners and other know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons, that the Leather made by the ſaid new Art, did far exceed all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Tannage, in this or other Nations, thereupon was pleaſed, upon the grain ſide of ſome of the ſaid Skins, to give an Epitomy of the real perfection, and excellency of the ſaid <hi>Mr. Duckets</hi> Art, and Ability to perform his undertakings for Improvement of Land and Leather; which for the Conciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them, being compoſed in a few lines in verſe, and ſo full of matter, that they could not be expreſſed in many ſheets in proſe, I therefore in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the gravity of the perſon and his verſes, and the Truth therein contein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with their juſt alluſions to honourable Atchievements, gainfull Inventions, and lively explanation of the Glory and Profit which might enſue to this Nation, could not contein my ſelf, but aſſume the boldneſſe, without their privity, to cauſe an impreſsion of the ſaid verſes, which may well merit peruſal and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration according to the humble conception of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A Faithfull Servant to the Author, And a Well-wiſher to the Common-wealth.</hi> Richard Cookson.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:14"/>
            <head>To his worthily honoured Friend <hi>Thomas Ducket Eſq</hi> upon his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearch into the Myſteries of Nature.</head>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jaſon</hi> brought the ſtock of fine-woold ſheep fi st into <hi>Spain. Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> taught Husbandry. The <hi>Chinois</hi> deviſed the making of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> diſhes. <hi>De Serres</hi> brought into <hi>France</hi> the making of ſilk. <hi>Columbus</hi> inriched <hi>Spain</hi> by diſcovering to them the Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Mines of <hi>India.</hi>
               </note>WHat praiſe brave <hi>Jaſon</hi> got of old,</l>
            <l>By bringing home the Fleece of Gold;</l>
            <l>What Fame Heroick <hi>Virgil</hi> wan,</l>
            <l>By ayding of the Husbandman;</l>
            <l>What benefit the <hi>Chinois</hi> found,</l>
            <l>In the right uſe of Purſline ground;</l>
            <l>What great advance <hi>De Serres</hi> made,</l>
            <l>By teaching <hi>France</hi> the Silkworms trade;</l>
            <l>What wealth <hi>Columbus</hi> did impart,</l>
            <l>To <hi>Spain</hi> by his Sea-faring Art;</l>
            <l>What renown did ere accrue,</l>
            <l>To the Inventors of things new,</l>
            <l>That worthy <hi>Ducket</hi> is thy due:</l>
            <l>And if authority ſhall ſtand,</l>
            <l>Thy Friend in theſe deſignes, this Land</l>
            <l>May as great praiſe and prize obtein,</l>
            <l>As <hi>Greece, Room, China, France</hi> or <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thy knowledge then let none cry down,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">The Author of theſe verſes doth allude the renown that <hi>England</hi> may poſſeſſe by the Propoſers Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, unto the good ſucceſſe that <hi>Spain</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth by that ſort of ſheep, that were at the firſt brought thither by the induſtry of <hi>Jaſon;</hi> The which ſheep were ſaid to bear Fleeces of Gold, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the moſt exquiſite fineneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Embleme of which Fleeces have been ever ſince worn as trophees of honour to the memory of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> upon the breaſts of the most famous Monarchs of Chriſtendome. And by that type or figure, it may as clear &amp; properly be ſaid that the Engliſh Cattel do bear golden hides &amp; skins, for that <hi>Mr. Ducket</hi> by his tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent new Art hath atchieved unto the glory and honour of converting them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to the moſt exquiſite Leather of the World in value and perfection. The Leather of the new make is very tough and ſtrong, and will not rot by wet, nor wear out neer ſo ſoon as Leather of the old make. This or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation that hath this skill may be inriched wher the Inventor doth communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note>That by thy Golden Skins is ſhewn,</l>
            <l>Made Leather without Bark at all,</l>
            <l>Corroſive Shumack, Salt, or Gall,</l>
            <l>Or any Compoſition which</l>
            <l>Beyond Seas came to make it rich;</l>
            <l>But with Ingredients of our own,</l>
            <l>Whoſe influence was never known:</l>
            <l>Which Leather makes that glory wins,</l>
            <l>As if our Beaſts had Golden Skins:</l>
            <l>Yet puts the Tanners Liquors down,</l>
            <l>That Leather makes ſo coarſe and brown;</l>
            <l>Compar'd with thine, it is but droſſe,</l>
            <l>An Embleme of the Worlds great loſſe.</l>
            <l>Which had continued but for thee,</l>
            <l>Throughout all times Eternity;</l>
            <l>Which now thy prudence can divert,</l>
            <l>When Honour ſhall advance thy Art:</l>
            <l>By turning Hides to Leather rare,</l>
            <l>In ſhew and gloſſe like Silken ware;</l>
            <l>Soft in the hand, white, plump, and full,</l>
            <l>Like felt well wrought of Beavers wool;</l>
            <l>In Colour, grain, in ſtrength and touch,</l>
            <l>The Vniverſe had never ſuch;</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:14"/>
            <l>Whoſe ſubſtance in the laſting wear,</l>
            <l>Doth exquiſite, and firm appear;</l>
            <l>And that which makes the profits large,</l>
            <l>'Tis done with little time and charge;</l>
            <l>Since in what Land thou doſt derive,</l>
            <l>Thy Science needs in wealth muſt thrive:</l>
            <l>Yea to confirm how well 'tis Tann'd,</l>
            <l>None of the Trade denyes his hand;</l>
            <l>But labours for thy Patents grant,</l>
            <l>Leſt we ſuch good ſhould longer want;</l>
            <l>And that by thy incouragement,</l>
            <l>We may enjoy whats eminent</l>
            <l>From others too who ſhall deviſe,</l>
            <l>Hereafter new diſcoveries.</l>
            <l>Beſides in Husbandry thou doſt,</l>
            <l>Supply with little pain and coſt,</l>
            <l>Where Nature to defect declines,</l>
            <l>In Barren Lands, Fruit, Trees, and Vines;</l>
            <l>What former Authors did not reach,</l>
            <l>Thy pregnant Judgement now can teach;</l>
            <l>New Methods of perpetual gain,</l>
            <l>Nature by Natures to ſuſtein:</l>
            <l>The drought of Land thou canſt prevent,</l>
            <l>By Art and watery Element;</l>
            <l>Thou canſt ſuppreſſe the force of weeds,</l>
            <l>That graſſe doth Choak, and kills good ſeeds;</l>
            <l>With wealthy ſecrets thou canſt fill,</l>
            <l>Thoſe Nations ſhall imbrace thy skill;</l>
            <l>Thou haſt recourſe to Natures ſtore,</l>
            <l>To fortunate both rich and poor</l>
            <l>With wealth of ſuch a large degree,</l>
            <l>That all good men will pray for thee;<note place="margin">The Author al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in ſeveral myſteries to the Mine &amp; Mint, in relation to his Theorical, Methodical, and practical parts, as alſo to his rich diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries that are of as great goodneſſe as mines of Gold.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Thy skill is ſuch, that to conclude,</l>
            <l>With what rare gifts thou art indu'd,</l>
            <l>Few can conceive in the extent;</l>
            <l>And what makes all more excellent,</l>
            <l>All's thine, to ſilence barking tongues,</l>
            <l>That to the Mine and Mint belongs:</l>
            <l>So that his parts muſt be Divine,</l>
            <l>Who can in part but add to thine.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ieremiah Collier.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133314:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
